<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The True cause of all our miseries, discovered in their visible effects as I find it (to my great satisfaction) most manifest, in The lay-man's religion, lately published, licensed, Octob. 1, 1690 : which vindicates the doctrine of the Church of England, (above all others,) to allow liberty of conscience, according to the tenour of the Gospel ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63461</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2593A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38360</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17349909</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17349909</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106392</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63461)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106392)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1105:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The True cause of all our miseries, discovered in their visible effects as I find it (to my great satisfaction) most manifest, in The lay-man's religion, lately published, licensed, Octob. 1, 1690 : which vindicates the doctrine of the Church of England, (above all others,) to allow liberty of conscience, according to the tenour of the Gospel ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Lay-man's religion.</term>
               <term>Second part of The lay-man's religion as an appendix to the first.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106392:1"/>
            <head>THE TRUE CAUSE Of all our MISERIES, Diſcovered in their Viſible Effects: As I find it (to my great Satisfaction) moſt manifeſt, in <hi>The Lay-man's Religion,</hi> lately publiſhed. Licenſed, <hi>Octob.</hi> 1. 1690.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Which vindicates the</hi> Doctrine <hi>of the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> England, <hi>(above all others,) to allow</hi> Liberty of Conſcience, <hi>according to the Tenour of</hi> the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Unveils the Undermining</hi> Jeſuite, <hi>and Deſigning</hi> Sectary: <hi>And detects the groſſeſt</hi> Frauds <hi>and</hi> Cheats, <hi>impoſed on the</hi> Honest, <hi>and</hi> Well-meaning, <hi>under the moſt</hi> ſacred Vizors <hi>and</hi> Pretences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Worthy to be received, and ſeriouſly conſidered of</hi> Miniſters of State, Lords, <hi>and</hi> Commons, <hi>as well as all other inferiour</hi> Subjects, <hi>(of every Perſuaſion,) in order to our laſting</hi> Safety <hi>and</hi> Settlement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We find it impoſſible to prevent the</hi> ſly <hi>and</hi> ſubtile Whiſpers <hi>of</hi> Deſigning Hypocrites; <hi>who in</hi> ſecret <hi>do miſ-repreſent the</hi> beſt <hi>of</hi> Their Majeſties Subjects, <hi>to create a</hi> Miſ-underſtanding <hi>of them, and their</hi> beſt Actions, <hi>only to gain a</hi> good Opinion <hi>of themſelves, and to carry on their own</hi> Deſigns. <hi>But none (without a Forehead of Braſs) dare openly queſtion ſuch experienc'd</hi> Truths, <hi>as have been exemplified in</hi> Bloody Tragedies, <hi>within the Compaſs of our own Memory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore it muſt be acknowledged, That</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whoever is the Author of that Book, he deals plainly and impartially with all; beginning</hi> at Home, <hi>with cenſuring the Criminals of his own Party, both Clergy and Layety; expoſing</hi> Hypocriſie <hi>and</hi> Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality <hi>(as the two Extremes) in All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore I have ſingled out this Sheet, as the beſt Service I can do Their Majeſties, and the Government; heartily wiſhing it might be diſtributed throughout the whole Kingdom, for Inſtruction to all, in order to ſecure and tranſmit our Civil and Religious Rights to Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: Which therein thus follows,</hi> Page <hi>21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS God Almighty hath various Ways and Methods to reform and diſcipline his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, according to their various Tempers and Diſpoſitions; ſo the Devil, by his Janizaries, <hi>Deſigning Hypocrites,</hi> and <hi>Time-ſervers,</hi> (who can readily take any Impreſſion in Religion, be of two or three perſuaſions at once, to promote their own <hi>Intereſt,</hi>) puts himſelf into various ſhapes, and baits his Hook with various Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106392:2"/>ſuited to mens different Inclinations, that he may catch both <hi>Phariſee</hi> and <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican;</hi> as well the <hi>ſpiritually proud,</hi> as the <hi>Debauchee,</hi> that no Fiſh may eſcape his Net, and (if it were poſſible) the Elect too ſhould be cheated by him.</p>
            <p>Thus he baits the <hi>Luxurious</hi> with <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> the <hi>Avaritious</hi> with <hi>Riches,</hi> and the <hi>Ambitious</hi> with <hi>Pride, Dominion,</hi> and <hi>worldly Deſign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he deſigns to ſubvert a Kingdom, or overthrow a Government, he doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear immediately in <hi>Arms</hi> and <hi>open Hoſtility;</hi> but firſt under a <hi>Diſguiſe</hi> of <hi>Zeal</hi> for <hi>Reformation,</hi> which he generally proſecutes, by removing all <hi>Foundation</hi> laid in the <hi>firſt Principles</hi> of <hi>Religion;</hi> and then proceeds to create various <hi>Opinions</hi> in the Minds of honest and well-meaning Perſons, of eaſie and credulous Diſpoſitions; continually raiſing <hi>Niceties</hi> and <hi>Scruples,</hi> (before any <hi>Foundation</hi> be laid in <hi>fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental</hi> Knowledge of the firſt Principles of our <hi>Religion,</hi> contained in the <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> the <hi>Ten Commands,</hi> and the <hi>Creed,</hi>) and thoſe <hi>Niceties</hi> and <hi>Scruples</hi> are more and more irritated by <hi>ſubtil</hi> and <hi>deſigning Teachers,</hi> under a <hi>Diſguiſe</hi> of <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God forbid <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> (if regulated by the Standard of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi>) as it is the Birthright of every Chriſtian, ſhould be denied to any that in ſincerity deſire it, to live peaceably under the <hi>Government in all Godlineſs and Honeſty;</hi> becauſe many perſons of honeſt and well-meaning Principles, may, from their <hi>Education in Foreign Parts,</hi> or in Families of <hi>different Perſuaſions,</hi> either miſapprehend, or not rightly underſtand the Truth of our Doctrine and Diſcipline eſtabliſhed among us.</p>
            <p>And many others, in the ſimplicity of their Hearts, when they ſee the <hi>vicious Lives</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> of ſome of our Members, or the <hi>Scandal</hi> of ſome of our <hi>Clergy,</hi> in things that are open and manifeſt, may be impoſed upon by <hi>Jeſuitical Whiſpers,</hi> on the one hand, and <hi>private inſinuating Teachers,</hi> on the other hand; as to imagine that our Religion eſtabliſhed, muſt either countenance or allow of ſuch Evils in the Profeſſors of it. Which is the Caſe of the Goſpel it ſelf</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as our Government is founded in the Law of God and Nature, and our Religion eſtabliſhed, is ſetled and framed from no other Model or Original but God's revealed Will in the Scriptures, and ſo both may be a juſt Standard for all other <hi>Governments;</hi> It muſt therefore be a Strain of great Arrogance and Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in any State-Mountebank to propoſe any Foreign Precedent for alteration of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>And to ſilence all Complaints but theirs, whom nothing leſs than All will ſatisfie, as our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> ſo eſtabliſhed, do allow a peaceable and innocent <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> the Grand Charter of Chriſtianity it ſelf; (which we have found by experience, no other differing Perſuaſion but ours would ever allow any longer than they wanted power to reſtrain it;) ſo none can deny it to be both prudent and juſt in the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> (from the Law of <hi>ſelf-preſervation,</hi>) to take care of, and ſecure it ſelf againſt all abuſe of ſo great a Bleſſing, by ſuch, who <hi>have pure Religion</hi> only in their <hi>Mouths,</hi> but the rankeſt Poiſon of <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>Worldly Deſign</hi> in their <hi>Hearts</hi> making no Scruple (as Opportunity ſerves,) to devour Widows Eſtates, as well as the Houſes and Patrimony of them and all others, to make way for their own <hi>Ambitious Deſigns;</hi> For we find it moſt certainly true, by woful experience, that <hi>it is impoſſible to ſecure any Government in the World on a laſting Foundation, but by annexing it to the Religion eſtabliſhed, ſo as to make them inſeparable, according to the Policy of</hi> New-England; (where <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> firſt planted their <hi>Law-makers.</hi>)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106392:2"/>
               <hi>They that do not firſt approve of, and embrace our Religion eſtabliſhed, ought to have no ſhare in our Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuch as would come into the <hi>Government</hi> on other Terms, have <hi>Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> only in their <hi>Mouths,</hi> but <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>Worldly Deſign</hi> in their <hi>Hearts;</hi> which they carry on by multiplying Sects, under ſeveral Leaders, (each ambitious to be Head of his own Party,) who, by their Influence on credulous and well-meaning Perſons, incloſe them, as in ſo many <hi>Peculiars,</hi> each Paſtor to incline and lead his own Flock; the only Method to divide, and conſequently to weaken both the Government, and Religion eſtabliſhed; that whenever their Intereſt is in danger, they may eaſily, (as hath been pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in like Caſes,) by the ſame Art, diſpoſe all, to unite (for the ſame End) againſt the Government they live under.</p>
            <p>And thus one and the ſame common (though inviſible) Enemy of Mankind, putting himſelf into various Shapes, and baiting his Hook with proper Objects, ſuited to Men's various Inclinations and Diſpoſitions, (which all centre in Self-Love,) can firſt divide and weaken, and again unite and deſtroy the beſt <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> in the World; though the deſigning Party are ever lurch'd in what they aim at, which is <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> and <hi>Rule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For no ſooner is any Party gotten uppermoſt, but the ſame Principle of Ambition and worldly Deſign animates the reſt (that are under) to <hi>ſupplant</hi> that, in order to advance themſelves into the <hi>Government;</hi> ſo that their whole <hi>Babel</hi> of <hi>Deſigning</hi> and <hi>Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,</hi> ever ends in <hi>Anarchy</hi> and <hi>Confuſion;</hi> which hath cauſed many of their <hi>chief Builders</hi> (convinced by their own woeful Experience) at laſt to acknowledge their <hi>Errour,</hi> and to declare, That <hi>to ſeek a Kingdom in this World by carnal Means</hi> and <hi>Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons is no true Badge of the bleſſed Redeemer's Followers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What clearer Demonſtration can we have, that there is always ſuch a <hi>deſigning</hi> Party at the Bottom, under the moſt ſpecious Vizor of <hi>Zeal for Reformation,</hi> and <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> than to ſee thoſe who pretend to the greateſt <hi>Purity</hi> and <hi>Sanctity</hi> (though of ſeveral Perſuaſions,) all to unite, and diligently to apply themſelves to ſuch <hi>Patrons</hi> and <hi>Leaders,</hi> whoſe Intereſt and Influence may beſt promote their Deſign, though they all know them to be of no Religion at all; nay, ſuch as are guilty of the greateſt<note n="*" place="margin">Flectere ſi nequeo ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros, Acheronta movebo.</note> 
               <hi>Immoralities;</hi> who can thunder out bloody Oaths without Reluctancy, and make uſe of their Power and Intereſt to oppreſs others, and ingroſs the Widow and Orphans Eſtates. Such Men as theſe are proper Objects of all the Courtſhip and Addreſs of thoſe conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Politicians; for they well know they are adapted for their Turn, who readily proſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their Conſcience to their Intereſt, can be moſt ſerviceable to their ambitious Deſigns. And as they are Favourites in the higheſt ſtation, ſo they are capable of the greateſt Acts of Oppreſſion and Injuſtice therein; as they may (by alienating the Hearts of Subjects) contribute more to dethrone a Monarch, or ſubvert a Government, than Ten Thouſand armed Men, eſpecially as thoſe deſigning Hypocrites manage it to their own Advantage; who, though they always carry the Flattery of a Loyal All hail in their Mouths; yet, by ſecret Trumpets in every Corner, they arraign the Prince himſelf, as Author of all Acts of Injuſtice and Oppreſſion, done by ſuch his Miniſters, to render Monarchy uneaſie to the People; and at the ſame time, with no leſs Induſtry, both in publick and private, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the moſt faithful and loyal Counſellors and Magiſtrates, who are moſt true to the Church and Government, and the very Pillars and Security of the Throne, as Betrayers of their Country, their Laws, and Liberty; rendring them odious to the Prince and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106392:3"/>People, that they may remove them, in order to get Champions and Agents of their own Faction, into all Places, and Offices of Truſt and Power, in the Government.</p>
            <p>This diſcovers plainly, that the Patrons and Clients are both governed by one and the ſame Principle of <hi>Self-Love,</hi> which ebbs and flows with their own Intereſt, the vital part of their Religion; and ſo diſpoſeth them to divide, or unite, against that which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth their Deſigns, and at length to quarrel among themſelves about (what they all aim at) <hi>Dominion</hi> and <hi>Rule.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Reſult of all which may be this; To put us upon a <hi>Modeſt Enquiry,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHat Endeavours have been made by all the <hi>ſeparate Congregations</hi> in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, towards an <hi>univerſal Reformation</hi> of <hi>Manners;</hi> and <hi>allaying</hi> our <hi>Heats,</hi> to <hi>heal</hi> our <hi>Diviſions,</hi> in order to Union among our ſelves; the only Means under Heaven, to ſecure us, in theſe perilous Times, againſt our <hi>Foreign Enemy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And wherein <hi>Chriſtian Charity,</hi> and <hi>Purity of Life,</hi> (farther than in the cheap and eaſie Fruit of the Lips,) hath appeared in <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> or thoſe that ſeparate from our <hi>National Communion,</hi> and pretend to <hi>Extraordinary Call,</hi> and <hi>Converſion,</hi> ſo as to diſtinguiſh them by any viſible <hi>Change</hi> in their Lives and Converſation, from thoſe of our <hi>Communion,</hi> who live according to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of our Church, or from what they themſelves have ever before been in their Life-time.</p>
               <p>And alſo, what viſible Effects the late <hi>Indulgence,</hi> granted to <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> hath wrought for the better, in procuring more <hi>meek, humble,</hi> and <hi>peaceable Spirits;</hi> or abating <hi>Pride, Murmuring,</hi> or <hi>Diſcontent;</hi> railing againſt, and cenſuring of others, (even among their own Party,) in order to heal our Breaches, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our Differences.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">It is manifeſt our Religion and Government is undermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: Therefore, O <hi>England, England!</hi> Conſider, in this thy Day, the Things of thy Peace, before it be too late. At laſt, for ſhame, lay aſide paſſionate Heat, and furious Zeal for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Intereſts, and (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Chriſtians) calmly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the publick Weal. Be wary (in Choice of Magiſtrates) of the two Extreams that poiſon all Religion and Morality; the Deſigning Hypocrite, and the Profane Atheiſt. Chuſe Men fearing God, and hating Covetouſneſs; ſuch as have been ſincere and conſtant to our Kingly Government, and Religion eſtabliſhed: And be wiſe as Serpents, to countermine and evade the moſt glorious and ſpecious Pretences of all others.</note>Nay, We may modeſtly enquire, whether the Scope and Tendency of all Endeavours in the <hi>Leading Party</hi> among them, hath not been more after <hi>Dominion</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> here below, than to advance the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> in the Hearts of Men? And, in order to that, Whether they have not, with the greateſt Subtilty and Partiality, improved their <hi>Factories</hi> and <hi>Agency</hi> by Humane Policy, to direct, order, or influence the Choice of Magiſtrates and Officers in every Colony among us, from whence the greateſt Heats and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances have ariſen, let the viſible Effects ſpeak for themſelves?</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:106392:3"/>
               <p>And when we have ſo done, we may (from the Hiſtory of the laſt Age) reflect upon that <hi>happy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> which continued among Proteſtants in this Kingdom, in the open Practice of <hi>Piety, Sobriety,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> from the firſt time of the <hi>Reformation;</hi> but eſpecially during the Forty four Years of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, when all (as one Soul) joyfully and conſtantly aſſembled together, at the ſet Times appointed by the Church, to celebrate <hi>Divine Service,</hi> and hear the <hi>Scriptures</hi> daily read; as the only Means to keep up a <hi>venerable Awe and Senſe of the holy Majeſty</hi> of God in the World, and in the Mind of every individual Perſon; and to maintain and increaſe <hi>Chriſtian Charity,</hi> and <hi>Brotherly Kindneſs,</hi> (the alone <hi>Medium</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> in a Kingdom;) as being all fully perſuaded in their Minds, it was a Service moſt acceptable to God; without any other Diſcipline, or Way of Worſhip, than what had been ſo ſetled among us by thoſe pious and learned <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> (the Founders of it,) who carried their own Faggots, <hi>(not loving their Lives unto Death,)</hi> to bear their Teſtimony for it.</p>
               <p>By which Means that happy Queen ſo long reigned in Peace, (by Love,) in the the Hearts of all her Subjects, and a <hi>Terrour</hi> to all her Enemies; whereby our <hi>National Church</hi> became the Envy of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the only Sanctuary for all <hi>diſtreſſed Proteſtants</hi> abroad.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All this plainly demonſtrates, That</hi> pure and undefiled Religion, <hi>founded in</hi> Piety, Sobriety, <hi>and</hi> Righteouſneſs, <hi>may be eaſily known of all, as it conſiſts in</hi> Humility, Self-denial, <hi>and</hi> ſincere Practice <hi>of what we know,</hi> (<hi>all epitomized in</hi> Good Living,) <hi>and not in</hi> profound Knowledge, needleſs Diſputes, long Prayers, or fruitleſs Diſcourſes.</p>
               <p>If theſe things were laid to heart, ſo as to be well weighed, and conſidered, by all <hi>ſincere</hi> and <hi>well meaning Chriſtians,</hi> who now ſeparate from our publick Communion, into private Congregations; that from thence they might be awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to examine, and (with me) ſeriouſly enquire into the Truth of Things, they would ſoon find how miſerably they have been impoſed upon, and drawn into Prejudice, and an ill Apprehenſion of the <hi>pureſt,</hi> and <hi>beſt eſtabliſhed Religion</hi> on the Earth, by ſuch deſigning Leaders, as can be contented to ſacrifice the Peace and Safety of the whole Kingdom, to promote the Intereſt of a Party, in order to gratifie their own <hi>Ambition,</hi> and <hi>Worldly Deſign,</hi> though under a Diſguiſe of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience;</hi> when in truth, by Separation from us, they do but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change one <hi>Shell of Religion</hi> for another; for ſo I reckon (and ſo our Church doth eſteem) the moſt reſined Diſcipline, or outward Way of Worſhip to be; and lays no more ſtreſs in it, than Decency and Order requires. Therefore it is no wonder that the moſt Ignorant, and Short-ſighted, and ſuch as look no farther into Religion than the <hi>outward Appearance,</hi> but are never capable of diſcerning the <hi>vital Subſtance,</hi> ſhould, from the Scandal of ſome wicked Members, (from which the <hi>Goſpel</hi> it ſelf was not wholly exempt,) be ſo apt to deſpiſe our eſtabliſhed Diſcipline, and yet at the ſame time idolize another Form, or Way of Worſhip; as if God were more pleaſed with one <hi>Shadow,</hi> than another.</p>
               <p>Whereas we eſteem our outward Diſcipline no otherwiſe than as outward Means, compoſed and adapted by the moſt pious and learned Men, from the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Fountain of the Scriptures, ſuited to every Capacity through a whole
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106392:4"/>Kingdom: the Leaſt Knowing, as well as the Moſt Learned; that all may joyn together. In which, the <hi>pious,</hi> and <hi>well-diſpoſed</hi> Chriſtian may worſhip God in the <hi>Beauty of Holineſs;</hi> and the <hi>Youth</hi> and <hi>Ignorant,</hi> as with a Leading-ſtep, may be trained up, from the firſt Principles of Religion, to the greateſt Perfection; and whereby alſo the <hi>Profane</hi> and <hi>Looſe</hi> are, by a venerable Authority, influenced and reclaimed, at leaſt kept within ſome Bounds, from <hi>ſcoffing</hi> at <hi>Religion;</hi> which is daily occaſioned by the Separation of ſuch who are ſtill ſubject (with their Neighbours) to the ſame Infirmities attending Humane Frailty, as well as to <hi>Pride, Ambition, Self-Love,</hi> (in the inordinate Love of the World,) <hi>Railing at,</hi> and <hi>Cenſuring</hi> of others, and yet, puffed up with a falſe Conceipt of their own Way, do herd and diſtinguiſh themſelves, under their ſeveral <hi>Leaders,</hi> into ſo many and various <hi>Ways, Opinions,</hi> and <hi>Perſuaſions;</hi> (I wiſh it were not ſo near a Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of the ſeveral Orders in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi>) and all under Conduct of their peculiar Guides.</p>
               <p>From whence it comes to paſs, that vain and looſe Perſons, beginning firſt with light Thoughts of Religion, and by degrees declining the publick Prayers of the Church, and private Family-Duties; and from thence giving ſcope to boundleſs Luſts, at laſt caſt off all Religion, and become downright <hi>Debauchees,</hi> and <hi>practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Atheiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This may ſatisfie any but ſuch as are in love with a falſe Perſuaſion, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand reſolved to know no better, that the Offence is taken, and not juſtly given, by thoſe that thus ſeparate from our National Communion; eſpecially when they may be all ſo clearly convinced, that the original Cauſe of Separation from our Communion did not ariſe from any thing either in our Doctrine, or the Diſcipline of our Church; but from what was acted by Temporal Rulers, (as they were ſteered by <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Intereſts,</hi>) in Eccleſiaſtical Courts, procuring a Toleration of <hi>Sports</hi> on the <hi>Lord's Day;</hi> and Indulgence to be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in other Matters, which our holy and pure Religion expreſly condemns and abhors; which could not but be very offenſive to many honeſt and well-meaning Perſons, eſpecially when ſo induſtriouſly improved by ſubtile <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> and whiſpering <hi>Sectaries,</hi> (the ſecret Enemies of our Church,) who inſinuated into the Minds of the Eaſie and Credulous, that our Religion did countenance ſuch Evils, and thereby drew them into <hi>ſeparate Congregations;</hi> whereby they had op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to introduce ſo many <hi>ſtrange Doctrines,</hi> and variety of <hi>Perſuaſions,</hi> the <hi>Seed</hi> and <hi>Cauſe</hi> of all our <hi>Heats, Diviſions,</hi> and <hi>Animoſities,</hi> on the one hand; and of <hi>Practical Atheiſm, Debauchery,</hi> and <hi>Immorality</hi> on the other: Both which (as groſs <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> and <hi>bare-faced Impiety</hi>) do equally expoſe us to the Divine Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, and lay us open to our Foreign Enemies. For it is moſt Plain, the <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick,</hi> as well as the <hi>Debauchee,</hi> when thwarted in their Deſigns, have an equal Tendency to <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Treaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay, were ſincere, (though miſ-perſuaded,) well-meaning Perſons but once fully ſenſible of theſe great Truths, and of the unavoidable Neceſſity of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning into our <hi>Communion,</hi> as the only Means left to unite and ſave us, by reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>True Piety,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Charity,</hi> in <hi>Sobriety</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> among us, it is impoſſible they ſhould ſleep quietly one Night, before they returned into this <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom</hi> of Safety: For (God knows) I fear there is no other <hi>Cure</hi> left for our univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Diſtemper; and it is high time to begin ſo happy a Work,</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:106392:4"/>
               <p>Wherein their <hi>Leaders,</hi> if they have (as they all pretend to have) the Spirit of <hi>Primitive Chriſtianity,</hi> may (as faithful in God's Vineyard) outſtrip all our <hi>idle Labourers</hi> in painful and powerful Preaching; and eſpecially, by their exemplary and holy Living, ſo influence their Doctrine on the Mind, as to reclaim many profane Perſons, who now take occaſion, from their Separation, into ſo many Forms and Shadows of Religion, to inveigh, and rail againſt them all.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>Lay-Menbers,</hi> if they return into our Communion, and live up to what our holy Religion (which is defective in nothing but <hi>good Living,</hi>) doth moſt plainly and powerfully teach, may boldly reprove, (by our <hi>Church-Authority,</hi>) and put to ſilence many open Tranſgreſſors, and <hi>Evil-doers,</hi> who now take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, from ſo many Faſhions of Religion among us, to deride and ſcoff at all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in general; and alſo (to their great comfort) may thereby ſhame a ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Clergy-Man into a Reformation of his Life, by ſaying, (with the Spirit of Meekneſs,) in the Language of the holy Prophet, <hi>I have more <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding than all my Teachers; for thy Teſtimonies are my Meditation,</hi> Pſal. 119.</p>
               <p>And this (I bear witneſs) is countenanced by all our reverend and pious <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> and <hi>Paſtors,</hi> who would have <hi>all come to the Knowledge and Practice of the Truth,</hi> and who (it is moſt manifeſt) are willing and ready to comply with any thing that may tend to heal our Breaches, and to purchaſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with their <hi>Diſſenting Brethren,</hi> if deſired in <hi>ſuch a way,</hi> and to be done in <hi>ſuch a manner,</hi> as may preſeve <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in the Church.</p>
               <p>Which we can never reaſonably hope ſhould be done, without ſome <hi>orderly Application</hi> of ſuch as muſt own themſelves <hi>inferiour</hi> to thoſe whom the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (under which they live) have made their <hi>Superiours;</hi> which nothing can hinder, or obſtruct, but <hi>Pride, Obſtinacy</hi> and <hi>Worldly Deſign,</hi> all which are directly contrary to the <hi>meek, yielding,</hi> and <hi>ſelf-denying Temper of Primitive Chriſtianity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here I may with an humble Confidence, inforce this Argument from the <hi>greateſt Example,</hi> and the moſt <hi>excellent Pattern;</hi> even that of His <hi>Sacred Majeſty,</hi> now in the <hi>Throne,</hi> the <hi>Head of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and <hi>Chief of our Communion;</hi> whoſe incomparable <hi>Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> (whether we conſider Him as a <hi>Man,</hi> or as a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi>) are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently known to the <hi>whole World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>WHO, to give us the cleareſt Evidence of his <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Sincrity,</hi> hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed himſelf to the greateſt Dangers, for Defence of the <hi>Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi> And though his Education was in a <hi>different Perſuaſion,</hi> (the <hi>Diſcipline eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed</hi> in his native Country;) yet, to demonſtrate both his <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Prudence,</hi> when he had ſearched into, and was fully ſatisfied, that the <hi>vital Part</hi> of that <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> wherein he was bred, and the Doctrine here taught in our <hi>National Church,</hi> was one and the ſame, he was neither tenacious in his own <hi>Opinion,</hi> nor bigotted to the outward <hi>Form,</hi> or <hi>Perſuaſion,</hi> (which is but the <hi>Cruſt</hi> and <hi>Shell.</hi>)</p>
               <p>But, (as beſt became the Head of his People,) he, together with his <hi>Royal Conſort,</hi> (as one Soul,) do openly profeſs our <hi>eſtabliſhed Religion;</hi> the greateſt Bleſſing Heaven could beſtow, if we know our Happineſs. And Oli that all Their Majeſty's Subjects would reſent it accordingly!</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:106392:5"/>
               <p>And farther, I might urge another eminent Inſtance in His <hi>Royal Highneſs</hi> the <hi>Prince of Denmark,</hi> whoſe Education was moſt ſtrict in the <hi>Lutheran Church,</hi> (the eſtabliſhed Religion of that Kingdom,) where the Diſcipline is as different from that of the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> as ours is from both; and yet, from the ſame <hi>Chriſtian Principle,</hi> founded in the vital Subſtance of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> and not wedded to the <hi>Shell</hi> and <hi>Shadow,</hi> finding the pure Doctrine ſtill the ſame, he joyns himſelf with His Sacred Majeſty, in the ſame Communion.</p>
               <p>Who both, during their late Expedition abroad, in the defence of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Country, have conſtantly, in a devout manner, offered up their Morning and Evening-Sacrifice at the <hi>Publick Prayers,</hi> according to the Diſcipline eſtabliſh'd in our Church.</p>
               <p>From whence we may appeal to all impartial Chriſtians herein, whether ſuch as are <hi>Natives</hi> of our own Country, and <hi>Fellow-Subjects</hi> with us in one Kingdom, and do all pretend to hold <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in Doctrine with the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> abroad, and with us too, in our <hi>National Church,</hi> and can ſo readily conform to the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions, Garb,</hi> and <hi>Attire</hi> of the preſent Age, and are apt enough to inſiſt upon the leaſt minute Particle of Precedency (with the reſt of Mankind) in <hi>Honour,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Order and Decency in <hi>Temporal Government;</hi> yet are ſo tenacious in their <hi>Opinion,</hi> and wedded to their own outward Form, or <hi>Shadow of Divine Worſhip,</hi> as, by a continued Separation, to ſacrifice our Religion, and the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of our Government, our <hi>Laws,</hi> our <hi>Liberties,</hi> and our <hi>Lives,</hi> as a Prey to our <hi>Foreign Enemies,</hi> rather than, with thoſe moſt <hi>Illuſtrious Perſons,</hi> and many other <hi>eminent modern Inſtances,</hi> (who were all as ſtrictly bred in different Perſuaſions, under Foreign Governments,) to <hi>embrace that holy and pure Religion,</hi> ſo here eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed and ſetled among us from the firſt Reformation, by thoſe <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>learned Martyrs,</hi> the Founders of it: I ſay, whether this <hi>Stiffneſs</hi> and <hi>Obſtinacy</hi> doth not ariſe from <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Prejudice</hi> in the honeſt and well-meaning, who are <hi>ſeduced,</hi> and <hi>impoſed</hi> upon; and from <hi>Self-Love, Ambition,</hi> and <hi>worldly Deſign</hi> in the <hi>Leaders</hi> and <hi>Seducers;</hi> rather than from any <hi>pure Principle</hi> of Primitive Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I leave to all Perſons concerned herein, to be themſelves Judges of the Matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I ſhall only add (to compleat this Diſcourſe) theſe following Paragraphs, out of the <hi>Second Part</hi> of the ſame <hi>Lay-man's Religion,</hi> publiſhed ſince the <hi>Firſt.</hi> Licenſed <hi>Nov. 13. 1690. Page 13.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I <hi>Do not hereby charge all Non-conforming Clergy,</hi> as culpable herein; (God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid:) For I am fully ſatisfied there are many reverend, pious, and ſincere Chriſtians of that number, who have great Veneration for our Eſtabliſhed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; yet have ſo far engaged themſelves in their different Perſuaſions, as they judge themſelves uncapable <hi>(Salva Conſcientia,)</hi> entirely to communicate with us, without ſome Accommodation in thoſe things which have hitherto obſtructed ſo happy an Union; to which, it is well known, the moſt holy and learned Fathers of our Church have been, and ſtill are, readily, and moſt willingly inclined, if ſuch Application were made as, according to the decent Rules of Civil and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Order in Government, is required.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:106392:5"/>
               <p>And to ſtop the Mouths of ſuch as endeavour to render ſuch an Accommodation either unpracticable, or impoſſible, whoever ſhall read, and will conſider the 34th <hi>Article</hi> of our Eſtabliſhed Religion, may be fully ſatisfied, that as the pious Founders of it took care nothing therein ſhould be repugnant to the Word of God, ſo they never intended the Rites and Ceremonies, (which are the Shadow, or Cruſt and Shell of Divine Worſhip,) eſtabliſhed in our Church, ſhould (like the Laws of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi>) be unalterable; thereby declaring plainly, that as thoſe Rites and Ceremonies might be changed, according to the diverſity of Countries, Times, and Manners of Men; ſo every particular, or National Church, (not particular Parties, or private Judgments,) hath Authority to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, change, or aboliſh them; <hi>ſo as all be done to edifying.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it cannot be reaſonably ſuppoſed, ſuch an eſtabliſhed Diſcipline (the alone <hi>Medium</hi> of Unity, and the Nerves and Sinews of all Government) ſhould be ſo from time to time changed, much leſs aboliſhed, to gratifie every Leader or Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of a Sect, or different Perſuaſion, that ſeparates from our publick Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, into gathered Churches, (though on never ſo ſpecious Pretences,) no more than may be reaſonably required of a Maſter of a Family to alter the Oeconomy of his Houſhold, to gratifie the Humour of every petulant Servant; or of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates in Corporations, to endanger the Peace and Safety of their Civil Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Government, by a Change or Alteration therein, only to remove or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Murmurs or Complaints of every diſcontented Citizen, that through Ignorance, Intereſt, or Deſign, ſhall ſcruple or refuſe to comply with the Rules and Orders made, long before they were there Inhabitants, for the Safety and Well-being of the Place. Every reaſonable and unbyaſſed Perſon, that ſhall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſider theſe things, and well weigh the Conſequence of it, muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily conclude, that ſuch a Condeſcention in Superiours herein, would quickly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinge all Government, and turn all ſetled Order, in the beſt Conſtitution in the World, into Anarchy and Confuſion.</p>
               <p>How infinitely happy then would it be for this Kingdom, if all that are Men of Learning and Parts, and every way fitly qualified for their high and holy Calling, (to whoſe Judgment I humbly ſubmit the Conſideration of theſe great and growing Evils,) would labour after ſuch an Accommodation, in ſo ſacred and weighty Affairs; that they might all, as Fellow-Labourers, join in the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and endeavouring after ſo deſirable a Bleſſing, as Harmony in Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; the only Means to heal our Diviſions, and effect an univerſal Reformation of Manners among us.</p>
               <p>For as it is moſt plain, Separation was the original Cauſe, and hath increaſed all our Miſeries; ſo nothing but ſuch an Union can heal and effect our Cure.</p>
               <p>God grant all Their Majeſties Subjects may approve themſelves herein, as worthy Members of ſuch a Communion, (in order thereto,) by following the Royal Pattern and Example of our Sovereign, and chief Member, himſelf, now on the Throne.</p>
               <p>But after all, I would be ſo underſtood, (as I have plainly, in the <hi>First Part,</hi> already declared,) that I do not aim at (in any thing I have ſaid) the leaſt Abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that honeſt and innocent <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> (the Chriſtian's Birth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:106392:6"/>
                  <hi>live peaceably under the Government, in all Godlineſs and Honeſty.</hi> But ſtill I ſay, it is both equal and juſt, that till ſuch Perſons ſhall be ſo rightly informed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced in their Judgments, as to <hi>conform to our Religion eſtabliſhed,</hi> they ought to be content with ſuch Liberty of Conſcience, and Indulgence, as the Law allows them, and not to make it a Stalking-horſe to ſerve their <hi>Worldly Intereſt, or Deſign;</hi> for it is from <hi>Lucifer,</hi> and not from <hi>Heaven,</hi> if they aſpire after, or attempt to ſhare in the Government, upon any other Terms.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop's Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
